Register of the James Burnham Papers, 1928-1983
Hoover Institution Archives
James Burnham Papers
1928-1983
88022
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (5.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to communism in the United States and abroad, the Congress for Cultural Freedom and other anti-communist movements in the United States and abroad, political conditions in the United States and the world, and conservative political thought.
Burnham, James, 1905-1987
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography
1905 Nov. 22 Born, Chicago, Illinois
1929-1942 Professor of Philosophy, New York University
1929-1933 Co-editor, Symposium
1931 Co-author (with Philip Wheelwright), Introduction to Philosophical Analysis
1941 Author, The Managerial Revolution
1943 Author, The Machiavellians
1947 Author, The Struggle for the World
1948 Author, The Case for De Gaulle (with Andre Malraux)
c. 1949-1953 Consultant, Central Intelligence Agency
1950 Author, The Coming Defeat of Communism
1953 Author, Containment or Liberation?
1954 Author, The Web of Subversion
1955-1977 Editorial Board, National Review
1959 Author, Congress and the American Tradition
1964 Author, Suicide of the West
1967 Author, The War We Are In
1987 July 28 Died, Kent, Connecticut
Congress for Cultural Freedom; Anti-communist movements--United States.; Anti-communist movements.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Conservatism--United States.; Journalists; Political science.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government.; World politics--1945-
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1928-1977
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, legal documents, clippings and other printed material, reports, and miscellany; includes material relating to James Burnham's work, employment, financial matters, health, family, and art collecting.
  - General. Correspondence, legal documents, printed material, and miscellany; includes material relating to employment, financial matters, health, family, and art collecting (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Analyses. Clippings, correspondence, and reports relating to James Burnham's work, 1948-1972 (Folder 2)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, c. 1930-1983
  Typescript and printed copies, serial issues, notes, reviews, memoranda, correspondence, and legal documents. Arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - General. Unidentified fragments, outlines, and typescripts, c. 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters to editors. Correspondence, typescripts, and printed copies, 1952-1953 (Folder 4)
    - Reviews. By James Burnham of works by others, 1947-1977 (Folder 5)
  - "Dialectic of American Foreign Policy," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - "How Democratic is America?" Typescript, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Statement on communism in education, Typescript and notes (Folder 8)
  - Symposium, Correspondence and contracts, 1964-1977. Primarily relates to an agreement to reprint specific volumes, 1964-1977, c. 1930-1933. (Folder 9)
  - The Managerial Revolution, 1941
    - General. Clippings, typescript drafts of introductions to several foreign language editions, and material relating to a review of the book by George Orwell, including a copy of the review, and James Burnham's letter to the editor in response, 1944-1965 (Folder 10)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated-1942 (Folder 11-12)
      - 1943-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "What Future for Free Enterprise?" Town Meeting, Printed copy and letter, 1942 Feb. 9. (Folder 2)
  - The Machiavellians, 1943. Clipping, preface to subsequent edition, and correspondence (with Henry Regnery and others), 1943-1971 (Folder 3)
  - "Is Russia Aiming at Post-War Domination of Europe?" Correspondence and a printed copy of a debate with Ely Culbertson, 1944 Feb. (Folder 4)
  - "The Sixth Turn of the Communist Screw," Partisan Review, Printed copy, 1944 Summer. (Folder 5)
  - "Stalin and the Junkers," Commonweal, Printed copy, 1944 Sept. (Folder 6)
  - The Struggle for the World, 1947
    - General. Review and a printed copy of a chapter excerpt entitled, "The Goal of Soviet Policy," American Mercury, 1947 April (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1967 (Folder 8)
  - "What is the Purpose of the United Nations?" Annals of the American Academy, Printed copy, correspondence, and clipping, 1947-1948, 1947 July. (Folder 9)
  - The Case for De Gaulle, 1948 (with Andre Malraux). Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Folder 10)
  - "How the United Nations Can be Made to Work," Reader's Digest, Correspondence, 1948, 1948 Jan. (Folder 11)
  - Memorandum on Titoism, 1949 Dec. (Folder 12)
  - "The Strategy of the Politburo and the Problem of American Counter-Strategy," Letter, reports, and typescripts, c. 1949-1950. (Folder 13)
  - The Coming Defeat of Communism, 1950. Reviews, typescripts, printed copy of an excerpt (in Japanese), and correspondence, 1950-1952 (Folder 14-15)
  - "What Can We Expect of Europe?" American Mercury, Letters, 1950, 1950 Feb. (Folder 16)
  - "Why Communism Will Fail," This Week, Letters, 1950, 1950 Feb. (Folder 17)
  - Article on psychological warfare, 1950-1951. Typescripts, memorandum, and correspondence (Paul Palmer, Reader's Digest) (Folder 18)
  - Statements, Congress for Cultural Freedom, Typescripts and clipping, 1951. (Folder 19)
  - "Parakeets and Parchesi: An Indian Memorandum," Partisan Review, Printed copy, 1951 Sept.-Oct. (Folder 20)
  - "The Humanities and the Law," New York University Law Review, Printed copy, 1952 Jan. (Folder 21)
  - "Philosophy of Communism," Naval War College Review, Printed copy, 1952 March. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Essay on foreign affairs, Partisan Review, Printed copy, 1952 May-June. (Folder 2)
  - "The Case Against Adlai Stevenson," American Mercury, Printed copy and correspondence (with Sidney Hook, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and others), 1952 July. (Folder 3)
  - "Democracy, Oligarchy and Freedom," Speech typecript, 1952 July 15. (Folder 4)
  - "How Long Will the Cold War Last?" Banking, Printed copy, 1952 Sept. (Folder 5)
  - What Europe Thinks of America (James Burnham, editor), Correspondence (Sylvain Troeder, Joseph Czapski, Raymond Aron, and others), and contract, 1953 (Folder 6)
  - Containment or Liberation? 1953. Reviews, correspondence (with H.V. Kaltenborn, Raymond Moley, and others), a broadcast transcript, and printed articles excerpted from the book entitled, "The East European Strategy," Ukrainian Quarterly, and "The Primacy of Politics," "Can Washington Conduct Political Warfare?", and "The Policy of Liberation," American Mercury, 1952-1953 (Folder 7)
  - "Can America Liberate the World?" This Week, Printed copy and correspondence, 1953 Feb. 8. (Folder 8)
  - "Critique of Containment" Freeman, Printed copy, 1953 Feb. 9. (Folder 9)
  - "Why Containment Must Go," New Leader, Printed copy, 1953 Feb. 16. (Folder 10)
  - Column on death of Stalin, Freeman, Printed copy, 1953 March 23. (Folder 11)
  - "What Will Happen to the Jews Behind the Iron Curtain?" National Jewish Monthly, Printed copy, 1953 April. (Folder 12)
  - "Was Bohlen a Blunder?" Freeman, Printed copy, 1953 May 4. (Folder 13)
  - "Editor Meets Senator," Freeman, Printed copy, 1953 June 15. (Folder 14)
  - " The Commonweal and McCarthyism," Commonweal, Printed copy, 1953 Aug. 28. (Folder 15)
  - Web of Subversion, 1954. Reviews, correspondence (with Paul Palmer, Benjamin Mandel, and others), memorandum (House Un-American Activities Committee), chart, and receipts, 1952-1968 (Folder 16)
  - "Do Europeans Really Hate Us?" This Week, Correspondence, 1954 Aug. 29. (Folder 17)
  - "Tribunes of the People," Freeman, Printed copies, 1955 Feb. (Folder 18)
  - "Kommunistische Unterwuhlung der Vereinigten Staaten," Schweizer Monatshefte, Printed copy and letter, 1955-1962, 1955 July. (Folder 19)
  - Interview, Typescript broadcast transcript, 1955 Sept. 22. (Folder 20)
  - "No Firecrackers Allowed," Freeman, Printed copy, 1955 Oct. (Folder 21)
  - "Why Not Investigate the Court?" National Review, Printed copy, 1957 July 20. (Folder 22)
  - Congress and the American Tradition, 1959. Correspondence (with Henry Regnery and others), contract, reviews, notes, outlines, typescripts, and printed material, 1955-1977 (Folder 23-36)
  - "Liberalism--Conservatism," Notes and outlines, c. 1960-1961. (Folder 37)
  - "Sticks, Stones, and Atoms," Ordnance, 1961. Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Folder 38)
  - Memorandum on foreign policy, Typescript, 1961 Feb. 15. (Folder 39)
  - "ADA: Our Number One Lobby," 1963. Correspondence (with Eugene Lyons, Benjamin Mandel, and others), typescript, printed material, and notes, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Suicide of the West, 1964. Correspondence (with Irving Kristol and others), notes, outlines, miscellany, clippings, articles, and other background material, reviews, and miscellany, 1961-1983 (Folder 2-4)
  - "Goldwater as Omen," Typescript and correspondence, 1964. (Folder 5)
  - "What's Wrong with the Cold War?" Typescript and correspondence, 1964. (Folder 6)
  - "Let Us Stand Firm in Vietnam," Letter and typescript apparently prepared for Senator Thomas Dodd, 1965 March. (Folder 7)
  - Statements on Vietnam, Typescript and correspondence, 1966. (Folder 8)
  - "Analysis of USIA: Program Books for Overseas Use," 1969. Correspondence (with Frank Shakespeare, Karl Baarslag, and others), clippings, memoranda, outlines, typescript, printed material, book lists, reviews, and other background material, 1968-1970 (Folder 9)
  - Memorandum of conversation with Juan Carlos of Spain, Typescript, 1969. (Folder 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1930-1983.
  General note
  NOTE: The bulk of this material relates generally to James Burnham's writings and political ideas; most correspondence relating to specific works is located in the SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series.
  Letters, biographical material, reports, memoranda, printed material, and miscellany. The bulk of this material relates generally to James Burnham's writings and political ideas, while most of the correspondence relating to specific works is located in the SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series. Includes correspondence neither to nor from James Burnham. Arranged alphabetically.
  - General
    - General
      - 1931-1949 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - 1950-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Family correspondence, 1920-1983 (Folder 4)
  - Albertini, G. ( Est & Ouest), 1968-1978 (Folder 5)
  - Amery, Julian, 1947-1964 (Folder 6)
  - Anders, Wladyslaw, 1950 (Folder 7)
  - Andrews, Robert Armstrong, 1950 (Folder 8)
  - Andrieu, Raymond, 1947-1950 (Folder 9)
  - Apert, Daniel, SEE ALSO: SUBJECT FILE/Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1950-1951. (Folder 10)
  - Aron, Raymond, 1950 (Folder 11)
  - Arzt, Arthur and Arno Siedel, 1948-1951 (Folder 12)
  - Aubert, Theodore, 1947-1948 (Folder 13)
  - Ayling, Alice, 1950-1952 (Folder 14)
  - Baarslag, Karl, c. 1969 (Folder 15)
  - Baczkowski, Wlodzimierz, Includes biographical sketches, and a report entitled "The National and Racial Minorities of Soviet Russia", 1950-1953. (Folder 16)
  - Baruch, Bernard, 1941 (Folder 17)
  - Benouville, General de, 1948 (Folder 18)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1950 (Folder 19)
  - Braam, H., 1948-1951 (Folder 20)
  - Brassert, Herman A., 1950 (Folder 21)
  - Bryan, Joe, 1947-1949 (Folder 22)
  - Buckley, F.R., 1965-1969 (Folder 23)
  - Buckley, James, Includes a memorandum on the SST and a typescript speech entitled, "What Americans Can Learn from Israel", 1971-1983. (Folder 24)
  - Buckley, Philip, n.d. (Folder 25)
  - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1964-1975 (Folder 26)
  - Burke, Arleigh, 1964 (Folder 27)
  - Burr, Nelson, 1947 (Folder 28)
  - Calmann-Levy, Robert, 1949-1969 (Folder 29)
  - Chang, Carsun, Includes correspondence with Chou Hsiang-kuang, 1951. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clay, Lucius, 1950 (Folder 2)
  - Cooke, Charles M., 1961 (Folder 3)
  - Copeland, Miles, 1970 (Folder 4)
  - Coste, Brutus, 1950-1976 (Folder 5)
  - Crozier, Brian, 1970-1976 (Folder 6)
  - Culbertson, Ely, 1949 (Folder 7)
  - Davidson, Eugene, 1960-1961 (Folder 8)
  - De Courcy, Kenneth, Includes a letter and clipping relating to Kenneth De Courcy, 1949-1964. (Folder 9)
  - Dennen, Leon, 1950 (Folder 10)
  - De Toledano, Ralph, 1950 (Folder 11)
  - Dewey, John, n.d. (Folder 12)
  - Dobriansky, Lev E., 1948 (Folder 13)
  - Dodd, Thomas J., 1962-1964 (Folder 14)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1964 (Folder 15)
  - Dowling, Allan, 1947 (Folder 16)
  - Draskovich, Slobodan, 1950 (Folder 17)
  - Eastman, Max, Relates to Max Eastman's condensation of two of James Burnham's books, 1950. (Folder 18)
  - Ellinger, Suzette, 1941-1950 (Folder 19)
  - Emmet, Christopher, 1950 (Folder 20)
  - Estonian National Council, 1948-1952 (Folder 21)
  - Fabre-Luce, Alfred, n.d. (Folder 22)
  - Fairbanks, Douglas, Jr., 1947 (Folder 23)
  - Feiffer, Jules, 1963 (Folder 24)
  - Fischer, Ruth, 1945 (Folder 25)
  - Friedman, Milton, 1953 (Folder 26)
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1971-1978 (Folder 27)
  - Garrity, Devin, 1950-1964 (Folder 28)
  - Gaulle, Charles de, 1953 (Folder 29)
  - Gautherot, Gustave, 1947 (Folder 30)
  - Genovese, Eugene, 1970 (Folder 31)
  - Gibarti, Louis, 1950-1951 (Folder 32)
  - Gow, James Steele, 1941 (Folder 33)
  - Grew, Joseph, 1954 (Folder 34)
  - Hegedus, Adam de, 1946-1947 (Folder 35)
  - Herberg, Will, 1943-1947 (Folder 36)
  - Herriot, Edouard, n.d. (Folder 37)
  - Hook, Sidney, 1949-1978 (Folder 38)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1947 (Folder 39)
  - Hornbeck, Stanley K., 1965-1966 (Folder 40)
  - Howe, Quincy, 1941 (Folder 41)
  - Hunt, E. Howard, Includes curriculum vita, 1962-1977. (Folder 42)
  - Isquith, Stanley, 1942-1943 (Folder 43)
  - Jackson, Henry M., c. 1963 (Folder 44)
  - Jolis, Albert, 1950 (Folder 45)
  - Kendall, Willmoore, 1965 (Folder 46)
  - Kennan, George, 1949 (Folder 47)
  - Kirk, Russell, 1964 (Folder 48)
  - Koestler, Arthur, Includes a clipping, 1949-1983. (Folder 49)
  - Krock, Arthur, 1964 (Folder 50)
  - La Follette, Suzanne, 1964 (Folder 51)
  - Lake, Harry B., 1941 (Folder 52)
  - Lasky, Melvin, 1950 (Folder 53)
  - Lazo, Mario, 1964-1967 (Folder 54)
  - League for Industrial Democracy, 1942 (Folder 55)
  - Liebman, Marvin, 1976-1981 (Folder 56)
  - Lindsay, A.O., 1943-1944 (Folder 57)
  - Luciolli, Mario, 1953-1963 (Folder 58)
  - Lundberg, Ferdinand, 1941 (Folder 59)
  - McCabe, Ralph, 1962-1964 (Folder 60)
  - McCaffrey, Neil, 1963-1975 (Folder 61)
  - Maestri Arredondo, Raul, 1947 (Folder 62)
  - Malraux, Andre, 1948-1953 (Folder 63)
  - Mandel, Benjamin, 1964 (Folder 64)
  - Manion, Clarence, 1965 (Folder 65)
  - Masani, Minoo R., Includes material relating to the Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1950-1983. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mauriac, Claude, 1951-1953 (Folder 2)
  - Mayence Research Associates (M.B. Somerfield, Director), Includes memoranda relating to inquiries about this organization, 1950-1951. (Folder 3)
  - Monnerot, Jules, 1950-1962 (Folder 4)
  - Moreell, Ben, 1964 (Folder 5)
  - Muhlen, Norbert, 1965 (Folder 6)
  - Mundt, Karl E., 1961 (Folder 7)
  - Nabokov, Nicholas, SEE ALSO: SUBJECT FILE/Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1950-1952. (Folder 8)
  - Nemo, Maxime, 1949-1963 (Folder 9)
  - Palmer, Paul ( Reader's Digest), 1963 (Folder 10)
  - Pemantle, Oscar, 1971 (Folder 11)
  - Percy, Charles H., Includes a memorandum by James Burnham relating to foreign policy positions in the Republican Party platform, 1960. (Folder 12)
  - Petrov, Vladimir, 1963-1970 (Folder 13)
  - Philbrick, Herbert, 1966 (Folder 14)
  - Phillips, William, 1967 (Folder 15)
  - Porzelt, Paul, 1964 (Folder 16)
  - Pound, Ezra, Includes cover letter from Henry Regnery, 1959. (Folder 17)
  - Proxmire, William, 1963 (Folder 18)
  - Regnery, Henry, 1960 (Folder 19)
  - Rickenbacker, Edward V., 1964 (Folder 20)
  - Rizzi, Bruno, 1951-1952 (Folder 21)
  - Roosevelt, Archibald B., 1941 (Folder 22)
  - Rummel, R.J., 1975 (Folder 23)
  - Sargeant, Porter, 1941 (Folder 24)
  - Schiff, Sydney, Includes correspondence between Schiff and David Burnham, and between James Burnham and individuals interested in the Schiff papers, 1930-c. 1976. (Folder 25)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr., 1951 (Folder 26)
  - Servan-Schreiber, Jean-Jacques, 1968 (Folder 27)
  - Soustelle, Jacques, 1960 (Folder 28)
  - Souvarine, Boris, 1950-1951 (Folder 29)
  - Strausz-Hupe, Robert, 1961 (Folder 30)
  - Strauss, Leo, 1964 (Folder 31)
  - Strauss, Lewis L., 1964 (Folder 32)
  - Tata, J.R.D., 1951-1952 (Folder 33)
  - Troeder, Sylvain, 1949-1960 (Folder 34)
  - United States Air Force, Air War College, 1948-1951 (Folder 35)
  - Utley, Freda, c. 1941-1943 (Folder 36)
  - Weyl, Nathaniel, 1966 (Folder 37)
  - Wells, H.G., 1942 (Folder 38)
  - Wheelwright, Philip, 1964 (Folder 39)
  - West, Rebecca, 1955 (Folder 40)
  - Williams, C. Dickerman, 1961-1968 (Folder 41)
  - Wills, Garry, n.d. (Folder 42)
  - Winsor, Curt, 1983 (Folder 43)
  - Wolfe, Bertram, 1969-1970 (Folder 44)
  - Wilkins, Sophie (Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.), 1969-1971 (Folder 45)
  - Wood, Richardson, 1960 (Folder 46)
  - Woolf, Virginia, Letter to unidentified correspondent (Folder 47)
  - Yarmolinsky, Adam, 1966 (Folder 48)
  - Young, Arthur, Includes reports and printed material, 1964-1977. (Folder 49)
  - Zawadowski, Zygmunt, 1950-1957 (Folder 50)
  - Zychlinski, L.W.S., 1965 (Folder 51)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1937-1983
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, newsletters, clippings, articles, pamphlets, and other printed material, lists, financial material, notes, transcripts, program statements, press releases, biographical material, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General. Correspondence, notes, biographical material, and miscellany,; includes material relating to trade, Latin America, and the United Nations, c. 1949-1981 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Africa. Correspondence (with Boris Souvarine, Eugene Lyons, Pedro T. Pereira, Portuguese Ambassador to the U.S., and others), clippings, reports, notes, and newsletters (Kenneth De Courcy),; includes material relating to Rhodesia, South Africa, and Russian influence in Africa, 1945-1976 (Folder 2)
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom. Correspondence (with Irving Kristol, Ralph De Toldedano, Albert Einstein, Sidney Hook, M.R. Masani, Arthur Koestler, Nicholas Nabokov, Irving Brown, Elliott Cohen, and others), financial statements, flyer, list, and reports (including material relating to immigration and the McCarran Act), 1950-1953 (Folder 3)
  - Asia. Correspondence, 1946-1977 (Folder 4)
  - Communism and anti-communism. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, bibliographies, conference material, report (Karl Wittfogel), bulletin (Socialist Party Convention, 1937), printed article (Boris Souvarine), and a program statement ("Theses of the Fourth Comintern Congress on the Negro Question"). Primarily correspondence (research inquiries) relating to James Burnham's participation in American Trotskyite organizations,; also includes material relating to Milton Sacks, 1937-1977 (Folder 5)
  - Congress for Cultural Freedom. Includes material relating to conferences in Berlin and New Delhi, the International Exposition of the Arts (Paris, and the establishment of a Japanese committee, 1952)
    - Correspondence. Daniel Apert, Arnold Beichman, Nicholas Nabokov, Louis Gibarti, Melvin Lasky, German Arciniegas, and others, 1950-1952 (Folder 6)
    - Non-printed material. Lists of delegates, reports, memoranda, speech notes, receipts, programs, and notes, 1950-1951 (Folder 7)
    - Printed material. Clippings, printed article, pamphlets, program; includes material by Melvin Lasky and Denis de Rougemont, 1950-1952 (Folder 8)
  - Davies, John Paton. Biographical material, correspondence (with Lyle Munson and others), letters to editors (Edgar Snow and James Burnham), and a broadcast transcript, 1946-1954 (Folder 9)
  - Defense and atomic weapons. Letter to the editor, minutes, memoranda, biographical material, article, and correspondence (Lawrence Hafsted and others),; includes material relating to J. Robert Oppenheimer, and to the deaths of Paul P. Stoutenburgh and family, 1947-1970 (Folder 10)
  - Europe. Correspondence, biographical material, memoranda, and reports,; includes material relating to Greece, post-World War II Germany, Eastern Europe, and France, 1947-1983 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Free Europe University (affiliated with the National Committee for a Free Europe, Inc.). SEE ALSO: Institut Litteraire ( Kultura)/Correspondence/Giedroyc, Jerzy. Primarily correspondence (with A.A. Berle, Jr., DeWitt Poole, Levering Tyson, Malcolm W. Davis, Lev Dobriansky, Anatol Muhlstein, and Boleslaw Wierzbianski); also includes memoranda, reports, draft press release, biographical material, and a clipping, 1949-1952 (Folder 2)
  - Institut Litteraire ( Kultura)
    - General. Notes, program proposals, financial material, report, printed material, and biographical material,; includes material relating to the Free Europe University and the Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1948-1969 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - General. Marvin Liebman, Zygmunt Nagorski, Lilly Endowment, Relm Foundation, Clarence Manion, Hobart Lewis, and others,; primarily relates to fund-raising efforts in conjunction with the Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America and the World Youth Crusade for Freedom, 1961-1971 (Folder 4)
      - Czapski, Joseph, 1948-1953 (Folder 5)
      - Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1949-1977 (Folder 6)
  - Lattimore, Owen. Reports by Owen Lattimore from Prague (1947), correspondence, printed material, subpoena (House Un-American Activities Committee), and statements (Pat McCarran), 1947-1953 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Milosz, Czeslaw. Corresopndence (with Jacques Maritain, Albert Einstein, and others), poem, memorandum, bibliography, typescripts, and affidavits (from James Burnham, Jerzy Giedroyc, Joseph Czapski, Sidney Hook, Nicholas Nabokov, and others),; relates to efforts to obtain a U.S. entry visa, 1951-c. 1971 (Folder 2)
  - National Review
    - General. Memoranda, notes, financial material, pamphlet, and circular,; SEE ALSO: CORRESPONDENCE FILE/Buckley, William F. and Kendall, Willmoore, 1955-1976 (Folder 3)
    - Pauling v. National Review. Correspondence (with C. Dickerman Williams, G. Albertini, Stephen Hugh-Jones, and others), pamphlet, and notes for testimony by James Burnham, 1964-1968 (Folder 4)
  - Organisation de l'Armee Secrete "Charlesmagne". Correspondence (Jean Parvulesco) and program statements (in French), 1951-1962 (Folder 5)
  - Russia. Correspondence, notes, and printed material, 1946-1976 (Folder 6)
  - United States - Politics. Correspondence, and reports,; includes material relating to Barry Goldwater, 1960-1970 (Folder 7)
  - Yugoslavia. Correspondence, memorandum, circular, 1951-1974 (Folder 8)
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, 1943-1969.
  See photo card catalog for description